In the last couple videos, we
Nos últimos vídeos,
talked about the ideas of
falamos sobre como,
how, first, if you're
se você receber características
given features for movies, you
determinadas para filmes,
can use that to learn parameters data for users.
pode usá-las para aprender parâmetros para usuários.
And second, if you're given parameters for the users,
Também, se você receber parâmetros para os usuários,
you can use that to learn features for the movies.
você pode usá-los para aprender características para os filmes.
In this video we're going
Neste vídeo, vamos
to take those ideas and put
pegar essas ideias e
them together to come up
juntá-las para chegar
with a collaborative filtering algorithm.
a um algoritmo de filtragem colaborativa.
So one of the things we worked
Uma das coisas que descobrimos
out earlier is that if
antes é que, se você
you have features for the
tiver características
movies then you can solve
para os filmes, pode resolver
this minimization problem to find
este problema de minimização para
the parameters theta for your users.
encontrar os parâmetros "θ" dos usuários.
And then we also
Também descobrimos que,
worked that out, if you
se você receber os
are given the parameters theta,
parâmetros "θ", você
you can also use that to
pode usá-los
estimate the features x, and
para estimar as características "x",
you can do that by solving this minimization problem.
resolvendo este problema de minimização.
So one thing you
Uma coisa que você
could do is actually go back and forth.
pode fazer é ir e voltar.
Maybe randomly initialize the parameters
Talvez inicializando aleatoriamente e
and then solve for theta,
solucionar em "θ",
solve for x, solve for theta,
depois em "x",
solve for x. But, it
depois "θ", depois "x".
turns out that there is a
Mas existe
more efficient algorithm that doesn't
um algoritmo mais eficiente que
need to go back and forth
não precisa ir e voltar
between the x's and the
entre os "x" e os "θ",
thetas, but that can solve
mas consegue
for theta and x simultaneously.
encontrar soluções para "θ" e "x" simultaneamente.
And here it is. What we are going to do, is basically take
Aqui está ele. Basicamente,
both of these optimization objectives, and
pegamos ambos os objetivos de minimização
put them into the same objective.
e juntamos no mesmo objetivo.
So I'm going to define the
Definirei o novo
new optimization objective j, which
objetivo de minimização "J",
is a cost function, that
uma função custo, que é
is a function of my features
uma função das
x and a function
características "x" e
of my parameters theta.
dos parâmetros "θ".
And, it's basically the two optimization objectives
Assim, é basicamente a
I had on top, but I put together.
junção dos dois objetivos.
So, in order to
Para explicar isso,
explain this, first, I want to point out that this
primeiro preciso mostrar que
term over here, this squared
este termo aqui, o termo
error term, is the same
de erro quadrático, é
as this squared error term and the
o mesmo termo que está aqui.
summations look a little bit
As somas parece um pouco
different, but let's see what the summations are really doing.
diferentes, mas vamos ver o que elas estão fazendo.
The first summation is sum
A primeira soma é
over all users J and
sobre todos os usuários "j", e a soma interna
then sum over all movies rated by that user.
é sobre todos os filmes avaliados pelo usuário.
So, this is really summing over all
Ou seja, uma soma por todos
pairs IJ, that correspond
os pares "(i, j)" que correspondem a um filme
to a movie that was rated by a user.
avaliado por um usuário.
Sum over J says, for every
A soma em "j" determina,
user, the sum of
para cada usuário, a soma de
all the movies rated by that user.
todos os filmes avaliados por ele.
This summation down here, just does things in the opposite order.
A soma aqui embaixo faz o mesmo, mas na ordem inversa.
This says for every movie
Ela determina,
I, sum over all
para cada filme "i", a soma
the users J that have
por todos os usuários "j"
rated that movie and so, you
que avaliaram o filme,
know these summations, both of these
portanto, ambas as somas
are just summations over all pairs
são por todos os pares "(i, j)"
ij for which
para os quais
r of i J is equal to 1.
"r(i, j) = 1".
It's just something over all the
É uma soma por todos os
user movie pairs for which you have a rating.
pares "(i, j)" para os quais existe uma avaliação.
and so those two terms
Assim, os dois termos
up there is just
de cima são exatamente
exactly this first term, and
este primeiro termo,
I've just written the summation here explicitly,
em que escrevi a soma explicitamente,
where I'm just saying the sum
por todos os
of all pairs IJ, such that
pares "(i, j)"
RIJ is equal to 1.
para os quais "r(i, j) = 1".
So what we're going
Então, o que fazemos
to do is define a
é definir um
combined optimization objective that
objetivo de otimização combinado
we want to minimize in order
que queremos minimizar para
to solve simultaneously for x and theta.
achar soluções em "x" e "θ" simulaneamente.
And then the other terms in
Os outros termos
the optimization objective are this,
no objetivo de minimização são: este,
which is a regularization in terms of theta.
que é um termo de regularização para "θ",
So that came down here and
que veio aqui embaixo,
the final piece is this
e a última parte é esta,
term which is
que está no
my optimization objective for
objetivo de minimização
the x's and that became this.
para os "x", que veio para cá.
And this optimization objective
Esse objetivo de otimização "J"
j actually has an interesting property
tem uma propriedade
that if you were to hold
interessante,
the x's constant and just
onde, deixando os "x" constantes
minimize with respect to the thetas then
e minimizando em "θ", você estará resolvendo
you'd be solving exactly this problem,
exatamente este problema,
whereas if you were to do
enquanto se fizer
the opposite, if you were to
o contrário,
hold the thetas constant, and minimize
deixando "θ" constante e minimizar
j only with respect to
"J" somente
the x's, then it becomes equivalent to this.
em relação aos "x", torna-se equivalente a isto.
Because either this term
Isso porque este termo
or this term is constant if
ou aquele será constante se minimizar
you're minimizing only the respective x's or only respective thetas.
somente em "x" ou somente em "θ".
So here's an optimization
Então, este é um objetivo
objective that puts together my
de otimização que junta
cost functions in terms of x and in terms of theta.
as funções custo em termos de "x" e "θ".
And in order to
Para chegar
come up with just one
ao problema de otimização
optimization problem, what we're going
único, o que
to do, is treat this
faremos será tratar
cost function, as a
a função custo como
function of my features
uma função das
x and of my user
características "x"
pro user parameters data and
e os parâmetros de usuário "θ"
just minimize this whole thing, as
para minimizar isso tudo,
a function of both the
como uma função
Xs and a function of the thetas.
tanto dos "x" quanto dos "θ".
And really the only difference
Na verdade, a única
between this and the older
diferença entre este
algorithm is that, instead
e o algoritmo anterior é
of going back and forth, previously
que, em vez de ir e voltar,
we talked about minimizing with respect
minimizando em "θ", depois
to theta then minimizing with respect to x,
minimizando em "x",
whereas minimizing with respect to theta,
depois em "θ",
minimizing with respect to x and so on.
depois em "x", e assim por diante.
In this new version instead of
Nesta nova versão, em vez de
sequentially going between the
ir sequencialmente pelos
2 sets of parameters x and theta,
dois conjuntos de parâmetros, "x" e "θ",
what we are going to do
o que faremos
is just minimize with respect
será simplesmente minimizar
to both sets of parameters simultaneously.
em ambos os conjuntos simultaneamente.
Finally one last detail
Finalmente, um último detalhe
is that when we're learning the features this way.
é que, quando aprendemos assim,
Previously we have been using
anteriomente tínhamos
this convention that
essa convenção de uma característica
we have a feature x0 equals
"x₀ = 1"
one that corresponds to an interceptor.
que corresponde a um termo de intercepção.
When we are using this
Quando usamos esse
sort of formalism where we're are actually learning the features,
formalismo onde estamos aprendendo as características,
we are actually going to do away with this convention.
vamos nos livrar dessa convenção.
And so the features we are going to learn x, will be in Rn.
Assim, as características "x" que vamos aprender estão em "ℝⁿ",
Whereas previously we had
em comparação
features x and Rn + 1 including the intercept term.
com as características em "ℝⁿ⁺¹" com o termo de intercepção.
By getting rid of x0 we now just have x in Rn.
Nos livrando de "x₀", temos "x ∈ ℝⁿ".
And so similarly, because the
Da mesma forma, como
parameters theta is in
os parâmetros "θ"
the same dimension, we now
têm a mesma dimensão,
also have theta in RN
também temos "θ ∈ ℝⁿ",
because if there's no
porque, se não existe
x0, then there's no need
"x₀", também
parameter theta 0 as well.
não há necessidade para o "θ₀".
And the reason we do away
Agora, estamos
with this convention is because
aprendendo todas
we're now learning all the features, right?
as características, certo?
So there is no need
Assim, não há necessidade
to hard code the feature that is always equal to one.
de estabelecer uma característica sempre igual a 1.
Because if the algorithm really wants
Isso porque, se o algoritmo
a feature that is always equal
realmente quiser
to 1, it can choose to learn one for itself.
uma característica igual a 1, pode aprender por conta própria.
So if the algorithm chooses,
Assim, se ele escolher,
it can set the feature X1 equals 1.
pode colocar "x₁ = 1".
So there's no need
Não há necessidade
to hard code the feature of
de forçar
001, the algorithm now has
"x₀ = 1", o algoritmo
the flexibility to just learn it by itself. So, putting
agora tem a flexibilidade para aprender isso por conta própria.
everything together, here is
Juntando tudo, aqui está nosso algoritmo
our collaborative filtering algorithm.
de filtragem colaborativa.
first we are going to
Primeiro,
initialize x and
inicializamos "x" e "θ"
theta to small random values.
a valores aleatórios pequenos.
And this is a little bit
Isso é um pouco
like neural network training, where there
como treinar redes neurais,
we were also initializing all the parameters of a neural network to small random values.
onde também inicializamos todos os parâmetros a valores aleatórios pequenos.
Next we're then going
A seguir, vamos
to minimize the cost function using
minimizar a função custo usando
great intercepts or one of the advance optimization algorithms.
gradiente descendente ou um dos algoritmos de otimização avançados.
So, if you take derivatives you
Encontrando as derivadas,
find that the great intercept
você descobre que as
like these and so this
atualizações do gradiente descendente
term here is the
são estas, onde este termo
partial derivative of the cost function,
é a derivada parcial da função custo,
I'm not going to write that out,
com respeito
with respect to the feature
à característica
value Xik and similarly
"x⁽ⁱ⁾ₖ", e, similarmente,
this term here is also
este termo aqui também
a partial derivative value of
é uma derivada parcial da
the cost function with respect to the parameter
função custo no
theta that we're minimizing.
parâmetro "θ" que estamos minimizando.
And just as a reminder, in
Só como um lembrete,
this formula that we no
nesta fórmula não
longer have this X0 equals
temos mais esse "x₀ = 1",
1 and so we have
ou seja,
that x is in Rn and theta is a Rn.
"x ∈ ℝⁿ" e "θ ∈ ℝⁿ".
In this new formalism, we're regularizing
Neste novo formalismo, estamos regularizando
every one of our perimeters theta, you know, every one of our parameters Xn.
todos os parâmetros "θ" e "x".
There's no longer the special
Não existe mais o caso
case theta zero, which was
especial "θ₀", que era regularizado
regularized differently, or which
de forma diferente,
was not regularized compared to
ou que não era regularizado
the parameters theta 1 down to theta.
comparado aos parâmetros "θ₁" a "θₙ".
So there is now no longer a
Agora não existe mais
theta 0, which is why
o "θ₀", e é por isso
in these updates, I did not
que não separei um
break out a special case for k equals 0.
caso especial para "k = 0".
So we then use gradient descent
Então, usamos gradiente
to minimize the cost function
descendente para
j with respect to the
minimizar a função custo
features x and with respect to the parameters theta.
"J" com respeito a "x" e "θ".
And finally, given a
E, finalmente, dado
user, if a user
um usuário
has some parameters, theta, and
com parâmetros "θ",
if there's a movie with
se existir um filme com
some sort of learned features x,
características aprendidas "x",
we would then predict that that
estimaríamos que o
movie would be given a
filme receberia
star rating by that user
uma nota igual a
of theta transpose j. Or
"θᵀ · x" do usuário.
just to fill those in,
Ou seja,
then we're saying that if user
se o usuário "j"
J has not yet
ainda não
rated movie I, then
avaliou o filme "i"
what we do is predict that
estimamos que
user J is going to
o usuário "j"
rate movie I according to
avaliará o filme "i"
theta J transpose Xi.
com a nota "(θ⁽ʲ⁾ᵀ) · (x⁽ⁱ⁾)".
So that's the collaborative
Esse é o algoritmo
filtering algorithm and if
de filtragem colaborativa, e
you implement this algorithm you actually get a pretty
se você implementá-lo, obterá um algoritmo
decent algorithm that will simultaneously
bem decente, que simultaneamente
learn good features for hopefully
aprende boas características para
all the movies as well as
todos os filmes, espero,
learn parameters for all the
além dos parâmetros para
users and hopefully give
todos os usuários,
pretty good predictions for how
e pode fornecer estimativas boas
different users will rate different movies that they have not yet rated
para as avaliações de usuários diferentes em filmes que ainda não viram.